A cold rain began to fall, and the blurred Street lamps looked ghastly in the dripping
mist. The public houses were just closing, and dim men and women were clustering in
broken groups around their doors. From some of the bars came the sound of
horrible laughter. In others, drunkards brawled and screamed. Lying back in the handsome with
his hat pulled over his forehead, Dorian Gray watched with listless eyes the
sworded shame of the great city, and now and then he repeated to himself the
words that Lord Henry had said to him on the first day they had met, “To cure the
soul by means of the senses, and the senses by means of the
soul.” Yes, that was the secret. He had often tried it, and would try it again
now. There were opium dens where one could buy oblivion, dens of horror where
the memory of old sins could be destroyed by the madness of sins that were
new. The moon hung low in the sky like a yellow
skull. From time to time a huge misshapen cloud stretched a long arm across and
hid it. The gas lamps grew fewer, and the streets more narrow and gloomy. Once the
man lost his way and had to drive back half a mile. A steam rose from the horse
as it splashed up the puddles. The side windows of the handsome were clogged
with a gray flannel mist.
“To cure the soul by means of the senses, and the senses by means of the
soul!” How the words rang in his ears! His soul, certainly, was sick to
death. Was it true that the senses could cure it? Innocent blood had been spilled.
What could atone for that? Ah! for that there was no atonement; but though
forgiveness was impossible, forgetfulness was possible still, and he was determined
to forget, to to stamp the thing out, to crush it as one would crush the adder
that had stung one. Indeed, what right had Basil to have spoken to him as he had
done? Who had made him a judge over others? He had said things that were
dreadful, horrible, not to be endured. On and on ploted the handsome
going slower, it seemed to him, at each step. He thrust up the trap and called to
the man to drive faster. The hideous hunger for opium began to gore at him.
His throat burned and his delicate hands twitched nervously together. He struck at
the horse madly with his stick. The driver laughed and whipped up. He laughed
in answer, and the man was silent. The way seemed interminable, and the streets like the
black web of some sprawling spider. The monotony became unbearable,
and as the mist thickened, he felt afraid.
Then they passed by lonely brick Fields The fog was lighter here, and he could
see the strange bottle shaped kils with their orange, fanlike tongues of fire. A
dog barked as they went by, and far away in the darkness some wondering seagull
screamed. The horse stumbled in a rut, then swerved aside and broke into a
gallop. After some time they left the clay road and rattled again over rough paven
streets. Most of the Wind windows were dark, but now and then fantastic shadows
were silhouetted against some lamp lit blind. He watched them
curiously. They moved like monstrous marionet and made gestures like live
things. He hated them. A dull rage was in his heart. As they turned a corner, a
woman yelled something at them from an open door, and two men ran after the
handsome for about a 100 yards. The driver beat at them with his
whip. It is said that passion makes one think in a circle. Certainly with hideous
iteration the bitten lips of Dorian Gray shaped and reshaped those subtle words
that dealt with soul and sense, till he had found in them the full expression, as
it were, of his mood, and justified, by intellectual approval, passions that
without such justification would still have dominated his temper. From cell to
cell of his brain crept the one thought; and the wild desire to live,
most terrible of all man’s appetites, quickened into force each trembling nerve and
fiber Ugliness that had once been hateful to him because it made things
real, became dear to him now for that very reason. Ugliness was the one
reality. The coarse brawl, the loathsome den, the crude violence of disordered
life, the very vess of thief and outcast, were more vivid, in their intense
actuality of impression, than all the gracious shapes of art, the dreamy
shadows of song. They were what he needed for forgetfulness. In three days he would be
free. Suddenly the man drew up with a jerk at the top of a dark lane. Over the
low roofs and jagged chimney stacks of the houses rose the black masts of ships.
Wreaths of white mist clung like ghostly sails to the
yards. “Somewhere about here, sir, ain’t it?” he asked huskily through the trap. Dorian
started and peered round. “This will do,” he answered, and having got out hastily and given the
driver the extra Fair he had promised him, he walked quickly in the direction
of the key Here and there a lantern gleamed at the stern of some huge
merchantmen The light shook and splintered in the puddles. A red glare came from an
outward-bound steamer that was coing The slimy pavement looked like a wet Macintosh
He hurried on towards the left, glancing back now and then to see if he was being
followed. In about 7 or 8 minutes he reached a small shabby house that was
wedged in between two gaunt factories. In one of the top Windows
stood a lamp. He stopped and gave a peculiar knock. After a little time he heard steps
in the passage and the chain being unhooked. The door opened
quietly, and he went in without saying a word to the squat misshapen figure that
flattened itself into the shadow as he passed. At the end of the hall hung a
tattered green curtain that swayed and shook in the gusty wind which had
followed him in from the street. He dragged it aside and entered a long low
room which looked as if it had once been a third rate dancing Saloon Shrill
flaring gas jets dulled and distorted in the fly blown mirrors that faced them,
were ranged round the walls. Greasy reflectors of ribed tin
backed them, making quivering discs of light. The floor was covered with ochre
colored sawdust, trampled here and there into mud, and stained with dark rings of
spilled liquor. Some Mala were crouching by a little charcoal stove, playing with
bone counters and showing their white teeth as they chattered. In one corner, with his head
buried in his arms, a sailor sprawled over a table, and by the torily painted
bar that ran across one complete side stood two haggard women, mocking an old
man who was brushing the sleeves of his coat with an expression of disgust. “He
thinks he’s got red ants on him,” laughed one of them, as Dorian passed by. The man
looked at her in terror and began to whimper. At the end of the room there was
a little staircase, leading to a darkened chamber. As Dorian hurried up its three
rickety steps, the heavy odor of opium met him. He heaved a deep breath,
and his nostrils quivered with pleasure. When he entered, a young man
with smooth yellow hair, who was bending over a lamp lighting a long thin pipe,
looked up at him and nodded in a hesitating manner. “You here Adrien muttered
Dorian. “Where else should I be?” he answered, listlessly. “None of the chaps will speak to me
now.” “I thought you had left England.” “Darlington is not going to do
anything. My brother paid the bill at last. George doesn’t speak to me either.... I
don’t care,” he added with a sigh. “As long
as one has this stuff, one doesn’t want friends. I think I've had too many
friends.” Dorian winced and looked around at the grotesque things that lay in such
fantastic postures on the ragged mattresses. The twisted limbs, the gaping
mouths, the staring lusterless eyes, fascinated him. He knew in what strange
heavens they were suffering, and what dull hells were teaching them the secret
of some new joy. They were better off than he was. He was prisoned in thought.
Memory, like a horrible malady, was eating his soul away. From time to time he
seemed to see the eyes of Basil hallwood looking at him. Yet he felt he could not
stay. The presence of Adrien Singleton troubled him. He wanted to be where no
one would know who he was. He wanted to escape from
himself I'm going on to the other place,” he said after a pause. “On the
warf Yes.” “That mad cat is sure to be there. They won’t have her in this place
now.” Dorian shrugged his shoulders I'm sick of women who love one. Women who
hate one are much more interesting.
Besides, the stuff is better.” “Much the same.” “I like it better. Come and have
something to drink. I must have something.” “I don’t want anything,” murmured the young
man. “Never mind Adrien Singleton rose up wearily and followed Dorian to the bar. A
halfcast in a ragged turban and a shabby ulster, grinned a hideous greeting as he
thrust a bottle of brandy and two tumblers in front of them. The women
sidled up and began to chatter. Dorian turned his back on them and said
something in a low voice to Adrien Singleton. A crooked smile, like a Malay
crease, writhed across the face of one of the women. “We are very proud tonight she
sneered. “For God’s sake don’t talk to me,” cried Dorian, stamping his foot on the
ground. “What do you want? Money? Here it is.
Don’t ever talk to me again.” Two red sparks flashed for a moment in the
woman’s Soden eyes, then flickered out and left them dull and
glazed. She tossed her head and raped the coins off the counter with greedy
fingers. Her companion watched her enviously. “It’s no use,” sighed Adrien
Singleton. “I don’t care to go back. What does it matter I'm quite happy here.” “You
will write to me if you want anything, won’t you?” said Dorian, after a pause.
“Perhaps.” “Good night, then.” “Good night,” answered the young man, passing up the
steps and wiping his parched mouth with a handkerchief. Dorian walked to the door
with a look of pain in his face. As he drew the curtain aside, a hideous laugh
broke from the painted lips of the woman who had taken his money. “There goes the
devil’s bargain!” she hied in aoar voice. “Curse you!” he answered, “don’t call
me that.” She snapped her fingers. “Prince Charming is what you like to be called,
ain’t it?” she yelled after him. The drowsy sailor leaped to his feet as she spoke,
and looked wildly round. The sound of the shutting of the
hall door fell on his ear. He rushed out as if in pursuit.
Dorian Gray hurried along the key through the drizzling rain. His meeting with Adrien Singleton
had strangely moved him, and he wondered if the ruin of that young life was
really to be laid at his door, as Basil hallwood had said to him with such infamy of
insult. He bit his lip, and for a few seconds his eyes grew
sad. Yet, after all, what did it matter to him? One’s days were too brief to take
the burden of another’s errors on one’s shoulders. Each man lived his own life
and paid his own price for living it. The only pity was one had to pay so often
for a single fault. One had to pay over and over again,
indeed. In her dealings with man, destiny never closed her
accounts. There are moments psychologist tell us, when the passion for sin, or for
what the world calls sin, so dominates a nature that every fiber of the body, as
every cell of the brain, seems to be instinct with fearful
impulses. Men and women at such moments lose the freedom of their will. They move
to their terrible end as automatons move.
Choice is taken from them, and conscience is either killed, or, if it lives at all,
lives but to give rebellion its fascination and disobedience its
charm. For all sins, as theologians weary not of reminding us, are sins of
disobedience. When that high spirit, that mourning star of evil, fell from heaven,
it was as a rebel that he fell callus concentrated on evil, with
stained mind, and soul hungry for rebellion, Dorian Gray hastened on,
quickening his step as he went, but as he darted aside into a dim archway, that had
served him often as a shortcut to the ill-famed place where he was going,
he felt himself suddenly seized from behind, and before he had time to defend
himself, he was thrust back against the wall, with a brutal hand round his throat.
He struggled madly for life, and by a terrible effort wrenched the tightening
fingers away. In a second he heard the click of a revolver, and saw the gleam of
a polished barrel, pointing straight at his head, and the dusky form of a short
thick set man facing him. “What do you want?” he gasped.
“Keep quiet,” said the man. “If you stir, I shoot you.” “You are mad. What have I done
to you?” “You wrecked the life of cibil vain was the answer, “and cibil vain was my
sister. She killed herself. I know it. Her death is at your door. I swore I would
kill you in return. For years I have sought you. I had no clue, no trace. The
two people who could have described you were dead. I knew nothing of you but the
pet name she used to call you. I heard it tonight by chance. Make your peace with
God, for tonight you are going to die.” Dorian Gray grew sick with fear. “I
never knew her,” he stammered. “I never heard of her. You are mad you'd better
confess your sin, for as sure as I am James vain you are going to
die.” There was a horrible moment. Dorian did not know what to say or do.
“Down on your knees!” growled the man. “I give you one minute to make your peace—
—no more. I go on board tonight for India, and I must do my job first. One minute.
That’s all.” Dorian’s arms fell to his side paralyzed with terror, he did not know
what to do. Suddenly a wild hope flashed across his brain. “Stop,” he cried. “How long
ago is it since your sister died? Quick, tell me 18 years,” said the man. “Why you
ask me? What do years matter 18 years,” laughed Dorian Gray, with a touch of
triumph in his voice 18 years! Set me under the lamp and look at my
face!” James vain hesitated for a moment, not understanding what was meant. Then he
seized Dorian Gray and dragged him from the archway. Dim and wavering as was the wind
blown light, yet it served to show him the hideous era as it seemed, into which
he had fallen, for the face of the man he
had sought to kill had all the bloom of boyhood, all the unstained purity of
youth. He seemed little more than a lad of 20 summers, hardly older, if older
indeed at all, than his sister had been when they had parted so many years ago.
It was obvious that this was not the man who had destroyed her life. He loosened
his hold and reeled back. “My God! my God!” he cried, “and I would have murdered
you!” Dorian Gray drew a long breath. “You have been on the brink of
committing a terrible crime, my man,” he said, looking at him sternly. “Let this be
a warning to you not to take vengeance into your own hands.” “Forgive me, sir,”
muttered James vain I was deceived. A chance word I heard in that damn den set
me on the wrong track.” “You had better go home and put
that pistol away, or you may get it into trouble,” said Dorian, turning on his heel
and going slowly down the street. James vain stood on the pavement
in horror. He was trembling from head to foot. After a little while, a black shadow
that had been creeping along the dripping wall moved out into the light
and came close to him with stealthy footsteps. He felt a hand laid on his arm
and looked around with a start. It was one of the women who had been drinking at the
bar. “Why didn’t you kill him?” she hissed out, putting haggard face quite close to
his. “I knew you were following him when you rushed out from DA's You fool! You
should have killed him. He has lots of
money, and he’s as bad as bad.” “He is not
the man I'm looking for,” he answered, “and
I want no man’s money. I want a man’s
life. The man whose life I want must be nearly 40 now. This one is little more
than a boy. Thank God, I have not got his blood upon my hands.”
The woman gave a bitter laugh. “Little more than a boy!” she sneered. “Why, man, it’s
nigh on 18 years since Prince Charming made me what I am.” “You lie!” cried James
vain She raised her hand up to heaven.
“Before God I am telling the truth,” she cried. “Before God?” “Strike me dumb if it
ain’t so. He is the worst one that comes
here. They say he has sold himself to the
devil for a pretty face. It’s nigh on 18
years since I met him. He hasn’t changed much since then. I have, though,” she added,
with a sickly Lear You swear this?” “I swear it,” came inoar echo from her flat
mouth. “But don’t give me away to him,” she whined I'm afraid of him. Let me have
some money for my Knight's lodging.” He broke from her with an oath and rushed
to the corner of the street, but Dorian Gray had disappeared. When he looked back,
the woman had vanished also